<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on main</title><link>https://clemak27.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in Home on main</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://clemak27.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About me</title><link>https://clemak27.github.io/cv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://clemak27.github.io/cv/</guid><description>Who am I? My name is Clemens and I currently work as a Software Engineer, maintaining and extending backend services.
Education I got a BSc in Computer Science at UAS Technikum Wien. I also studied physics for a while until I figured out it wasn&amp;rsquo;t for me.
Coding I mainly use Java, Go and Java-/Typescript (in nodejs) for programming, but I&amp;rsquo;m not afraid to try something new. There&amp;rsquo;s also an interest in DevOps and I have a server at home running Fedora CoreOS.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="who-am-i">Who am I?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My name is Clemens and I currently work as a Software Engineer, maintaining and
extending backend services.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="education">Education&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I got a BSc in Computer Science at UAS Technikum Wien. I also studied physics
for a while until I figured out it wasn&amp;rsquo;t for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="coding">Coding&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I mainly use Java, Go and Java-/Typescript (in nodejs) for programming,
but I&amp;rsquo;m not afraid to try something new. There&amp;rsquo;s also an interest in DevOps
and I have a server at home running Fedora CoreOS. Automating all the boring
stuff is also a worthwhile goal. I also find the whole Nix ecosystem both
awesome and fascinating. I have a gitea instance where I keep all my private
repos, the code I feel confident/important enough to share is on GitHub.
I&amp;rsquo;m a Linux user and do all of my editing in neovim and IntelliJ.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="music">Music&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I mostly listen to progressive rock and other slightly weird music.
I&amp;rsquo;m also not averted to more classical music and soundtracks. Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve
also explored a more ambient/electronic sound. I also picked up a guitar at the end
of 2021 but stuggle to find time to practise it. I also plan on learning more
about music production and synthesizers in the future or might pick up a keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For reference, these are more or less my favorite artists (in no particular order):&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ayreon&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Devin Townsend&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dream Theater&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nightwish&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Opeth&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pink Floyd&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Porcupine Tree&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Riverside&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Steven Wilson&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tool&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="space">Space&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Space has always fascinated me since my childhood, both the scientific
background and its exploration by humanity. One of the reasons I started
studyíng physics was exactly this fascination.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sci-fi">Sci-Fi&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I enjoy watching science fiction movies (and playing scifi games) that are both
entertaining and thought-provoking. Bladerunner 2049 is a good example for that
(and also visually beautiful in my opinion). Finding time to watch everything I
want is hard though.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sports">Sports&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not really into sports (and not very sporty myself). I used to watch
Formula 1 in the past though. I also like walking/hiking to places.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gaming">Gaming&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I do enjoy a good game from time to time. I used to play quite a lot
on nintendo consoles when I was younger, nowadays I mostly enjoy indie
and older titles on my PC. I also spend way too many hours playing
Guild Wars when I was a teenager. Just don&amp;rsquo;t ask me about my opinion on
Guild Wars 2, it&amp;rsquo;s complicated.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>About this page</title><link>https://clemak27.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://clemak27.github.io/about/</guid><description>This site was created by me, using hugo.</description><content>&lt;p>This site was created by me, using &lt;a href="https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo">hugo&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>homelab</title><link>https://clemak27.github.io/homelab/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://clemak27.github.io/homelab/</guid><description>I have a small server at home, running some services host for myself. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if you can even call a single server homelab, but hey, it&amp;rsquo;s something. ¯\_(ツ)_/¯
My server is a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; PC with a Node 304 as a case, an AMD Ryzen 5 3600 with 16 GB and currently 8TB HDD (with space for more). It run Fedora CoreOS. All services on it run in docker-containers. Nothing of those is public, and only accessible via VPN.</description><content>&lt;p>I have a small server at home, running some services host for myself.
I don&amp;rsquo;t know if you can even call a single server homelab,
but hey, it&amp;rsquo;s something. ¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My server is a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; PC with a Node 304 as a case, an AMD Ryzen 5 3600 with
16 GB and currently 8TB HDD (with space for more). It run Fedora CoreOS.
All services on it run in docker-containers. Nothing of those is public,
and only accessible via VPN. It uses PiHole to resolve urls to the server&amp;rsquo;s ip
and traefik to point the server&amp;rsquo;s urls to the container ports.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also have a Raspberry Pi 3 laying around that might get (re-)integrated
into my Homelab later.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I would also like to experiment with k8s more,
but with just a single server, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it will give me much benefit
unfortunately (and the hardware prices are still a bit too high
to invest some money in that).&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Linux Setup</title><link>https://clemak27.github.io/linux_setup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://clemak27.github.io/linux_setup/</guid><description>dotfiles etc. are here
My journey so far My Linux journey took me to many distributions over the years:
Linux Mint Guess everyone had to start somewhere ¯\_(ツ)_/¯. For the things I did back then, which was mostly taking notes for university classes and some simple programming, it was ok. Cinnamon was also fine at the beginning, coming from Windows.
Ubuntu After that, I used vanilla Ubuntu for a while (back in a time where it was still kinda ok and not full of snaps).</description><content>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/clemak27/linux_setup">dotfiles etc. are here&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="my-journey-so-far">My journey so far&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My Linux journey took me to many distributions over the years:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="linux-mint">Linux Mint&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Guess everyone had to start somewhere ¯\_(ツ)_/¯. For the things I did back
then, which was mostly taking notes for university classes and some simple
programming, it was ok. Cinnamon was also fine at the beginning, coming from Windows.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ubuntu">Ubuntu&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>After that, I used vanilla Ubuntu for a while (back in a time where it was still
kinda ok and not full of snaps). I thought the way GNOME worked with the
different workspaces was cool.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="kubuntu">Kubuntu&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I soon switched to KDE Plasma in the form of Kubuntu. Which was awesome, all the
things you could customize. The whole set of KDE software is also more up
my alley than their GNOME equivalents.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="manjaro">Manjaro&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>While I was occasionally still dual booting windows until now, it was finally
time to use Linux all the time, also on my desktop PC. I needed and wanted more
up to date software for this, so I switched to a rolling release distro and
ended up with Manjaro. The few months I used it, it was quite ok, and also
supported my hardware well. That said, there were and still are some concerns
with Manjaro (there a good writeup &lt;a href="https://manjarno.snorlax.sh/">here&lt;/a>).
So I just went to use Arch proper.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="arch-linux">Arch Linux&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Despite the common opinion, I found Arch actually be easy to install, the guide
in the archwiki is pretty detailed. I also soon began documenting and automating
the install process to fit my needs in case I wanted to start fresh. That said,
Arch has been extremely stable for me and the legendary wiki and a community has
a wealth of knowledge if one encounters problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the years I used Arch, I also learned a lot of new things about the inner
workings of Linux. This was also the time-period where I learned to love vim,
which I use daily now. While still staying with Plasma most of the time, I also
used i3 for a while (and took one or 2 looks what GNOME is up to)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While Arch really is awesome (and I would everyone interested in Linux to at
least try it out for a while) there were also a few things that annoyed me.
As already said, I documented my whole setup and ended up with some pretty
convoluted install scripts. That said, such scripts take also time to maintain,
and testing them would usually mean spinning up a VM etc. Not to mention the
not-so-nice experience of not writing down a magic command that fixes an issue.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="nixos">NixOS&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I eventually came to know the Nix ecosystem. After using the (community made)
home-manager tool to manage my dotfiles, I took the plunge and replaced
Arch with NixOS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are 2 things I find great about Nix: The whole system-configuration in
declared in one file, and the system is setup exactly the way it is defined,
with all packages and customizations. The second is the awesome nix_shell,
that creates local development environments in an awesome way. Want to see how
your node14 application works with node16? Just create a nix-shell without
screwing up your global install or setting up nvm.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="fedora-silverblue">Fedora Silverblue&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Despite my initial hype for NixOS I was not 100% satisfied with it.
I switched to Fedora Silverblue. I like its combination of containers,
flatpaks and the toolbox. That said, I currently still use home-manager
to organize my dotfiles, which is both because it would require addidtional
migration work, and because it allows me to use my dotfiles anywhere else where
Nix is available. While I did think about returning to NixOS for a while,
I see no reason to change fot now. Fedora just works™&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>